{
  "reference_number": "9857",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "I support this option because it will hold future governments to account - if a target is changed, that government will have to justify it\n\n and consult on it."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "New Zealand is a very small emitter globally, but per capita we are large emitters. We should view this as a multi-generational\n challenge and commit to international climate leadership by setting a very ambitious goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "An international credit market (that is audited and overseen by international institutions) is a reasonable way to make reductions. In\n\n some cases it may also support industries in developing nations to make climate reductions also, which is positive. However,\n domestic reductions should certainly be the largest share of our efforts."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "All legislation is changeable, and regular reviews are sensible. As above, any changes that loosen the regime will have to be made\n\n public, which should hold future governments accountable. There should be statutory consultation requirements in provisions which\n allow for amending the targets, including for a Climate Commission to make recommendations, and for the government to respond to\n them."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This provides a level of certainty, and will allow for long term policy planning by industry and government."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "As above, robust consultation requirements will be necessary. It would be foolish to think that one government will automatically be\n bound by another's decisions in these matters, but it will be important that a broad consensus is formed on these matters. The\n\n independent climate commission should play a large role in informing government."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But the independent climate commission should be empowered to speak out where opportunism reduces the committments in the\nbudget beyond what is necessary"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Though i would dde-emphasise the focus on taxation and public borrowing - these considerations may have too short-term a focus\nrelative to a multi-generational issue like climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "How government will support industries and communities to adapt - climate migration, ie where funding for research etc will come\n\nfrom. Govt should also consult young people (primary and secondary schools) given that those people will bear the burden of failed\nclimate action."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Providing the commission is truly independent, it should be empowered to set this itself. However there will always be a risk that\ngovernment will overrule it."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - but I would put science at the top by far."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Recent cases of communities possibly needing to relocate (Franz Josef, Edgecumbe) mean that New Zealand, led by central\n\ngovernment, needs to understand more about the impacts of climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "In consultation with industry and community - possibly pooling funds (matched by Government) could improve this scheme."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I strongly support reducing emissions in New Zealand. Any scheme needs to include and account for all sources of emissions\n\nincluding urban traffic, agriculture, and industry. Robust transition planning needs to be support, accompanied by well-funded\nresearch into mitigating emissions while retaining valuable industries.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
